Welcome to Meeting Your Self.
This practice is an invitation to connect
with the core of you that can bring calm,
curiosity, compassion, clarity, courage,
confidence, creativity, and
connectedness.
Beneath the busy thoughts, the worries,
the roles you play, and the emotions that
come and go, there may be a steadier
presence within you. In IFS, we call this
Self-energy.
You do not have to make Self-energy
happen.
You are simply creating space to notice
what is already available, even if it is
only a small glimmer.
Begin by finding a comfortable position.
You may close your eyes, soften your
gaze, or look gently at one steady point.
Let your hands rest.
Let your shoulders soften.
Let your breath be natural.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Again, breathing in.
And breathing out.
Now begin to notice your body.
Notice your feet.
Your legs.
Your hips.
Your back.
Your chest.
Your shoulders.
Your arms.
Your hands.
Your neck.
Your face.
You do not have to relax everything.
Just notice.
Now bring your attention inside.
Ask gently:
What parts of me are present right now?
You might notice a busy part.
A tired part.
A worried part.
A part that wants to do this correctly.
A part that does not want to do this at
all.
A part that feels curious.
A part that feels guarded.
All parts are welcome to be noticed.
Now ask:
How do I feel toward these parts?
If you feel open, kind, or curious,
notice that.
If you feel frustrated, impatient,
afraid, blank, or judgmental, notice that
too.
That may mean another part is blended.
Nothing is wrong.
If there is a part judging or managing
the experience, gently acknowledge it.
You might say inside:
I see you trying to help.
You don’t have to go away.
Would you be willing to give me just a
little space so I can listen?
Notice what happens.
<break time="3s"
/>
Even a tiny bit of space matters.
Now imagine your inner system like a
room.
Or, if it feels more natural, imagine
your Self as a wide sky. Thoughts may be
clouds passing through. Emotions may be
weather moving across the horizon. The
sky does not have to push anything away.
It simply has space to hold what is here.
Parts may be standing close.
Some may be far away.
Some may be hidden.
Some may be loud.
Some may be quiet.
And somewhere in this room, there is also
the possibility of Self-energy.
Not as a perfect state.
Not as something you have to perform.
Just as a steady presence.
Begin with calm.
Notice whether there is even one percent
more calm available.
Maybe in your breath.
Maybe in your hands.
Maybe in the space around you.
Now curiosity.
Can you be just a little curious about
what is happening inside, without needing
to fix it?
Now compassion.
Is there any part of you that could
receive a little kindness?
Even if compassion feels far away, maybe
you can notice the wish for compassion.
Now clarity.
Is there anything you can see a little
more clearly about your inner world right
now?
Now courage.
Is there a small brave step in simply
being present with yourself?
Now confidence.
Not forced confidence.
Just the possibility that you can be with
what is here, one breath at a time.
Now creativity.
Maybe your system has more options than
it first seemed.
Maybe something new can happen slowly.
Now connectedness.
Notice your connection to your body, to
the room, to this moment, and to the
parts of you that are trying in their own
ways to help.
Now silently ask:
What quality of Self-energy feels most
available right now?
And ask:
What part of me needs that quality most?
If a part comes forward, imagine offering
that quality gently.
Not pushing it.
Not overwhelming it.
Just letting it be near.
You might say:
I am here.
I want to understand.
You do not have to carry this alone.
Notice what happens inside.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now take a slow breath.
And let your attention widen.
Feel the support underneath you.
Notice the room around you.
Notice sounds.
Notice light.
Notice your body.
Before you finish, ask yourself:
What is one Self-energy quality I want to
carry into the rest of my day?
When you are ready, gently return.
And as you move back into your day,
remember: Self-energy does not have to
arrive as a grand experience. Sometimes
it begins as one softer breath, one
moment of curiosity, one kind word toward
a part. That is enough. You can return
here, one breath at a time.