Welcome to Cultivating Self Qualities.
In this practice, we will gently explore
the eight C’s of Self: curiosity,
calmness, compassion, confidence,
courage, creativity, clarity, and
connectedness.
You do not need to feel all of them.
You are simply noticing what is available
and what may be asking for support.
Begin by settling your body.
Let yourself arrive.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Now notice what is present inside.
Maybe thoughts.
Maybe sensations.
Maybe emotions.
Maybe parts.
Let everything be here without needing to
change it.
We will begin with curiosity.
If imagery feels supportive, you might
imagine curiosity as a warm golden light
in the mind's eye — not bright or
forceful, just gently illuminating what
is here.
Curiosity is the quality of turning
toward your inner world with interest
instead of judgment.
<break time="3s"
/>
Ask inside:
What am I noticing right now?
Now ask:
Can I be just a little curious about
this?
If curiosity is not available, notice the
part that blocks it.
That part may have a good reason.
Now calmness.
Calmness does not mean everything is
peaceful.
It may simply mean there is a little more
space around what is happening.
Notice your breath.
Notice the support underneath you.
Ask:
Is there any place inside or around me
that feels even slightly calmer?
Now compassion.
If imagery feels supportive, you might
imagine compassion as a soft warmth
around the heart — like sitting near a
quiet hearth on a cold day.
Compassion is the ability to be with pain
without turning against it.
Ask:
Is there a part of me that could use
kindness right now?
If compassion feels difficult, ask:
What part of me is afraid of compassion?
Now confidence.
Confidence in IFS does not mean forcing
certainty.
It means sensing that you can be present
with your parts, even slowly.
Ask:
What helps me trust myself, even a
little?
Now courage.
Courage may be the willingness to notice
something honestly.
Ask:
What feels brave about being here with
myself right now?
Now creativity.
Creativity is the possibility that there
may be new choices.
Ask:
What new option might my system not have
considered yet?
Now clarity.
Clarity is seeing what is happening
without becoming completely blended with
it.
Ask:
What do I understand a little more
clearly right now?
Now connectedness.
If imagery feels supportive, you might
imagine all the qualities gathering as a
soft white-gold light in the heart — not
to erase your parts, but to remind them
that they belong.
Connectedness may be connection to your
body, to your parts, to another person,
to the present moment, or to something
larger.
Ask:
What helps me feel less alone?
Now take a moment to notice which Self
quality felt most available today.
And which quality felt least available.
There is no failure here.
The less available quality may show you
where a protective part needs attention.
Now imagine placing the most available
quality near a part of you that needs
support.
If calmness was available, let calmness
be near that part.
If curiosity was available, let curiosity
gently turn toward that part.
If compassion was available, let
compassion soften around that part.
Silently say:
I do not need to become perfect.
I can practice returning to Self-energy.
One quality at a time is enough.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
When you are ready, return your attention
to the room.
Notice one Self quality you want to carry
with you today.
Let that quality be like a small lantern
you do not have to hold perfectly. It can
flicker. It can be faint. It can still
help you find your way back.