Welcome to Meeting Your Inner Child.
This practice is an invitation to gently
connect with a younger part of you.
You are always allowed to go slowly.
You are allowed to stop.
You are allowed to keep your eyes open.
You do not need to force any memory,
image, or feeling.
Begin by settling into a comfortable
position.
Let your body know that, in this moment,
you are here.
Take a slow breath in.
And release it.
Now notice the room around you.
Notice one thing you can see.
One thing you can feel.
One thing you can hear.
Let this help orient you to the present
moment.
Now imagine, if it feels okay, that there
is a safe inner place.
This place can be real or imagined. It
might have warm light, soft colors, a
steady sound, or a sense of quiet
protection.
It might be a room.
A garden.
A beach.
A forest.
A cozy chair.
A place with warm light.
Let it be simple.
You are not forcing anything.
You are creating a place where a younger
part could feel safe enough to be
noticed.
Now ask inside:
Is there a younger part of me that would
like to be known today?
If nothing comes, that is okay.
You can simply sit in this safe place and
offer kindness to any younger parts who
may not be ready.
If a younger part does appear, notice how
close or far away they are.
<break time="3s"
/>
Notice their age, if you sense one.
Notice their expression.
Notice their posture.
Notice what they might be feeling.
You do not need to move toward them too
quickly.
Ask inside:
Is it okay if I notice you?
If the answer feels like no, respect
that.
You can stay at a distance.
If the answer feels like yes, imagine
offering a gentle presence.
Now ask this younger part:
What do you want me to know?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
You may hear words.
You may sense feelings.
You may notice images.
You may simply feel something in your
body.
Let it be enough.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now ask:
What was hard for you?
And then:
What did you need that you did not
receive?
If this feels tender, let yourself slow
down.
You do not have to fix it all.
You are simply witnessing.
Now notice how you feel toward this
younger part.
<break time="3s"
/>
If you feel compassion, warmth, or
sadness, let that be here.
If you feel numb, distant, annoyed, or
unsure, notice that too.
That may be another protective part.
You can acknowledge it gently.
If it feels right, say to the younger
part:
I see you.
I believe that this was hard.
You deserved care.
I am here with you now.
Notice how the younger part responds.
<break time="3s"
/>
You might ask:
What would help you feel a little safer
right now?
Maybe they want space.
Maybe closeness.
Maybe a blanket.
Maybe a kind word.
Maybe a place to play.
Maybe simply not to be rushed.
Imagine offering only what feels welcome.
Now thank this younger part for showing
up in whatever way they did.
Let them know you can return slowly.
You do not have to leave them behind.
You can imagine placing them somewhere
safe and comfortable inside.
Now begin to notice your adult body
again.
Your breath.
The surface under you.
The room around you.
Take one slow breath in.
And let it out.
When you are ready, gently return.
You do not have to complete the whole
story today. Simply noticing a younger
part with care is already a meaningful
act of repair. You can come back slowly,
with patience, warmth, and respect.
------------------------------------------
------------------------------.