Welcome to this reparenting meditation.
This practice is about offering care,
protection, and presence to a younger
part of you.
It is not about forcing forgiveness,
forcing healing, or pretending the past
did not matter.
It is about bringing Self-energy to a
part that may have needed more than it
received.
Begin by settling your body.
Let yourself arrive slowly.
Take a gentle breath in.
And breathe out.
Feel the support underneath you.
Let your body know that you are here now.
If at any point this feels like too much,
you can open your eyes, look around the
room, move your body, or stop the
practice.
You are in charge of the pace.
Now imagine a safe place inside.
It can be simple.
A warm room.
A quiet garden.
A safe porch.
A peaceful beach.
A soft blanket.
Let the place form in whatever way it
wants to.
Now ask inside:
Is there a younger part of me that needs
care today?
If a younger part appears, notice them
gently.
If no part appears, imagine sending care
to any younger part who may need it
later.
Notice this younger part.
How old do they feel?
What are they wearing?
How close or far away are they?
What emotion do they seem to carry?
Before moving closer, ask:
Would it be okay if I came a little
closer?
Respect whatever you sense.
If the part needs distance, stay at a
distance.
Distance can still be caring.
Now ask:
What did you need back then?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Maybe they needed protection.
Maybe comfort.
Maybe someone to believe them.
Maybe someone to stay.
Maybe someone to explain that it was not
their fault.
Maybe someone to let them be a child.
Now ask:
What do you need from me now?
You do not have to promise anything
impossible.
Offer what is true and gentle.
You might say:
I am here now.
I want to understand what happened to
you.
You did not deserve to be alone with
that.
You do not have to carry this by yourself
right now.
Notice how the younger part responds.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now imagine offering the kind of care
that feels welcome.
Maybe sitting beside them.
Maybe wrapping them in a blanket.
Maybe holding their hand.
Maybe protecting the doorway.
Maybe telling them they are not in
trouble.
Maybe letting them play.
Maybe simply staying near.
Now ask:
Is there anything you wish someone had
said to you?
If words come, imagine saying them
gently.
If no words come, simply offer presence.
Now ask:
Would you like to show me anything about
what you went through?
If the part shows something, remember:
you do not have to go into every detail.
You can witness just enough.
You can say:
I believe this was hard.
I am listening.
We can go slowly.
Now imagine bringing in more support.
Maybe your adult Self.
Maybe a wise figure.
Maybe light.
Maybe a protective presence.
Maybe other caring parts of you.
Let this younger part know they do not
have to be alone.
Now ask:
What would help you feel safer as we
close this practice?
Imagine offering that.
A safe room.
A comforting object.
A protective boundary.
A reminder that you can return.
Now gently thank this younger part.
You might say:
Thank you for letting me know you.
I will keep learning how to care for you.
We can take this one step at a time.
Now begin to return to your present-day
body.
Feel your feet.
Your hands.
Your breath.
The support underneath you.
Look around the room if your eyes are
open.
Or imagine the room around you if your
eyes are closed.
Orient to the present.
Take one slow breath in.
And let it out.
When you are ready, return fully.
Carry this connection gently. Reparenting
is not about becoming perfect. It is the
steady practice of returning, listening,
protecting, and offering care one honest
moment at a time.