Welcome to Inner Child Play.
This practice is an invitation to
reconnect with playfulness, imagination,
and joy.
You do not have to feel playful right
away.
Sometimes playful parts are hidden behind
protectors.
That is okay.
Begin by settling your body.
Take a gentle breath in.
And let it out.
Now notice any part of you that reacts to
the idea of play.
Maybe a part feels excited.
Maybe a part feels silly.
Maybe a part feels embarrassed.
Maybe a part says, this is pointless.
All of that is welcome.
Now ask inside:
Is there a younger part of me that
remembers play, or wishes it had more
room to play?
If a younger part appears, notice what
kind of play it is drawn toward.
Maybe drawing.
Dancing.
Building.
Running.
Singing.
Pretending.
Exploring.
Laughing.
Making something.
Being messy.
Being free.
Ask this part:
What kind of play did you love, or wish
you had?
Now imagine creating a safe play space
for this part.
It might be a room full of art supplies.
A backyard.
A playground.
A beach.
A pile of blankets.
A music room.
A magical world.
Let it be whatever this part wants.
Now ask:
What would you like to do here?
Imagine allowing this younger part to
play without criticism.
No one is judging.
No one is rushing.
No one is grading the outcome.
If a critical or embarrassed part
appears, gently acknowledge it.
You might say:
I see you.
You may be trying to protect me from
feeling foolish.
You do not have to disappear, but maybe
you can give this younger part a little
room.
Now return to the younger part.
Let it have a few moments of play.
Notice what happens in your body as this
part plays.
<break time="3s"
/>
Maybe warmth.
Maybe sadness.
Maybe resistance.
Maybe lightness.
Maybe nothing obvious.
Whatever happens is okay.
Now ask the younger part:
What do you want me to remember about
play?
And:
What is one small playful thing I could
let into my real life?
It could be tiny.
A color.
A song.
A doodle.
A silly movement.
A few minutes outside.
A playful object.
A moment of imagination.
Now thank this younger part for showing
you something.
Let them know play does not have to be
earned.
Joy does not have to be perfect.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Return to the room around you.
And consider one small way to let play
have a little space today.
Your playful parts do not need to prove
their usefulness. Joy, imagination,
wonder, and silliness are not
distractions from healing. Sometimes they
are part of how healing finds its way
back into the body.
------------------------------------------
------------------------------.