Welcome to this unblending practice.
In IFS, blending happens when a part’s
feelings, thoughts, or impulses feel like
all of who you are.
Unblending means creating a little space
so you can relate to the part instead of
being completely inside it.
You might imagine the feeling as a cloud
in the sky of your awareness. It can
still be present, but it does not have to
be all of you.
You do not have to push any part away.
We are simply practicing space.
Begin by settling.
Let your body be supported.
Take a slow breath in.
And breathe out.
Now notice what part of you feels most
present right now.
It might be anxious.
Critical.
Numb.
Angry.
Sad.
Driven.
Avoidant.
Overwhelmed.
Or something else.
Choose one part to gently focus on.
Not the most overwhelming one if that
feels like too much.
Just one part that is available to
notice.
Now ask:
Where do I notice this part in or around
my body?
Maybe in the chest.
The throat.
The stomach.
The jaw.
The shoulders.
The head.
The hands.
Or maybe it feels outside the body.
Now ask:
How blended am I with this part from zero
to ten?
Zero means you feel completely separate
from it.
Ten means it feels like all of you.
Just notice the number.
Now gently say to this part:
I see that you’re here.
I know you may be trying to help.
I’m not trying to get rid of you.
I would like to understand you from a
little more space.
Now ask the part:
Would you be willing to give me just a
little space?
Notice what happens.
<break time="3s"
/>
If the part says no, that is okay.
Ask:
What are you afraid would happen if you
gave me space?
Listen gently.
If the part is willing to give space,
notice whether it moves.
Maybe it steps back.
Maybe it softens.
Maybe it becomes less intense.
Maybe nothing changes.
All of that is okay.
Now ask again:
How blended do I feel with this part now,
from zero to ten?
If the number changed even a little,
notice that.
If it did not change, that is still
useful information.
Now see if you can feel any Self-energy
toward this part.
Maybe curiosity.
Maybe compassion.
Maybe patience.
Maybe simply the willingness to keep
listening.
Ask the part:
What do you want me to know?
And:
What are you trying to protect me from?
Thank the part for showing you whatever
it showed you.
Even if you do not understand it fully
yet.
You might say:
I am learning how to be with you.
We can go slowly.
You do not have to carry this alone.
Now let your attention widen.
Feel your whole body.
Feel the room.
Feel the support underneath you.
Take one final breath in.
And let it out.
When you are ready, return.
Even a small amount of space is
meaningful. You are practicing the
difference between being taken over by a
part and being with a part. That
difference is one doorway back to
Self-leadership.
------------------------------------------
------------------------------.