Welcome to the Parts Council Meditation.
This is a more advanced practice.
It is an invitation to listen to several
parts from Self-energy, without forcing
agreement or resolution.
If at any time this feels overwhelming,
you can pause, open your eyes, return to
your breath, or stop.
Begin by settling into your body.
Let yourself arrive.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Notice the room around you.
Notice that you are here, in the present
moment.
Now imagine a safe council space inside.
This might be a circle of chairs.
A quiet room.
A fire circle.
A garden.
A conference table.
A place in nature.
Let it be a space where parts can gather
without being forced.
Now invite Self-energy to be present at
the center of this space.
Not as a boss.
Not as a judge.
But as a calm, curious, compassionate
presence.
Now ask:
Which parts want to be represented in
this council today?
Let parts appear one at a time.
There may be a manager.
A critic.
A protector.
A tired part.
A young part.
A reactive part.
A part that wants control.
A part that wants escape.
Let whoever comes be noticed.
Now choose one part to speak first.
Ask:
What do you want the council to know?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now thank that part.
Let it know it has been heard.
Now invite another part to speak.
Ask:
What do you want the council to
understand?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Thank that part.
Now notice if any parts disagree with
each other.
Maybe one part wants closeness and
another wants distance.
One wants rest and another wants
achievement.
One wants expression and another wants
silence.
This is polarization.
It does not mean anything is wrong.
It means parts are trying to protect in
different ways.
Ask the council:
What are you each trying to protect?
Now ask:
What are you afraid would happen if you
stopped doing your job?
Listen without rushing.
Now invite Self-energy to speak, if it
feels available.
Not to command the parts.
Not to fix them.
But to offer presence.
You might silently say:
I hear that each of you is trying to
help.
I do not need you to agree immediately.
I want to understand what each of you
carries.
Now ask the parts:
What do you need from Self right now?
Maybe they need patience.
Reassurance.
Protection.
A plan.
Rest.
Clarity.
Time.
Respect.
Imagine offering what feels possible.
Only what feels honest.
Now notice if any younger or more
vulnerable part is nearby.
Do not force it to come forward.
Just notice.
If a vulnerable part is present, ask the
protectors:
Would it be okay if I simply notice this
part, without overwhelming it?
Respect the answer.
Now return to the whole council.
Ask:
What is one thing you want me to remember
after this practice?
Let each part offer a word, image,
feeling, or message.
Now thank the council.
Thank the parts that spoke.
Thank the parts that stayed hidden.
Thank the protectors.
Thank the vulnerable parts.
Thank the system for allowing this much
contact.
Imagine closing the council respectfully.
Parts can return to their places.
The room remains available for future
meetings.
Nothing has to be finished today.
Now return to your body.
Feel your breath.
Feel your hands.
Feel the surface under you.
Notice the room.
Notice the present moment.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
When you are ready, gently return.
You do not have to make every part agree
today. The council can remain open inside
you — a place where each voice can be
heard, where protection can soften over
time, and where Self can keep learning
how to lead with steadiness and care.