Welcome to Working with Firefighters.
In IFS, firefighter parts often react
quickly when something feels too painful,
too intense, or too much.
They may distract, numb, escape, shut
down, act impulsively, or create urgency.
This practice is not about shaming those
parts.
It is about understanding what they are
trying to protect.
Begin by settling into your body.
Let your breathing be natural.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Now gently ask:
Is there a reactive or urgent part of me
that I can notice today?
This might be a part that wants to avoid.
A part that wants to numb.
A part that wants to distract.
A part that wants to lash out.
A part that wants to disappear.
A part that wants immediate relief.
Choose one firefighter part to focus on.
Only choose one that feels safe enough to
notice right now.
Now ask:
How do I feel toward this part?
If you feel judgment, fear, anger, or
shame toward it, that is understandable.
See if you can notice those reactions as
parts too.
Now gently turn toward the firefighter
part and say:
I know you may be trying to help.
I am not here to shame you.
I want to understand what you are
protecting.
Now ask:
What do you do when you take over?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now ask:
What are you trying to stop me from
feeling?
And:
What are you afraid would happen if you
did not act quickly?
Let the answers come slowly.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now ask:
How long have you been doing this job?
And:
What happened that made this job feel
necessary?
You do not have to go into every memory.
Just notice what the part wants you to
know.
Now see if you can appreciate the
protective intention.
Even if the strategy has consequences.
Even if the strategy causes problems.
The part may be trying to keep you from
unbearable pain.
You might say:
Thank you for trying to protect me.
I understand that you learned to act
fast.
I want to help so you do not have to work
so hard.
Now ask:
What would you need in order to trust me
a little more?
Maybe the part needs proof.
A plan.
Support.
Boundaries.
Reassurance.
A different way to handle intensity.
Now ask:
Would you be willing to pause for just
one breath before acting next time?
If the part says yes, thank it.
If it says no, ask what it would need
first.
Now imagine offering this part a small
alternative.
Not a command.
Just a possibility.
Maybe breathing.
Texting support.
Taking a walk.
Using the app.
Writing in virtual paper.
Naming the part.
Putting a hand on your chest.
Ask:
Which alternative feels least
threatening?
Now thank this firefighter part.
Let it know you are beginning to
understand.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Return to the room.
And remember: this part does not need to
be defeated.
It needs to be understood, supported, and
gradually relieved of its extreme job.
The firefighter is not the enemy. It is
often a tired guardian standing near an
old fire. With patience, trust, and
support, it may not have to work so hard.