Welcome to the Cultivating Self Energy
Practice.
This practice is an invitation to
strengthen your connection with the
steady, compassionate center of your
system.
Self-energy does not need to be forced.
It is not a performance. It is the part
of you that can notice, listen, care, and
respond with more spaciousness.
Begin by finding a comfortable position.
Let your body be supported.
Let your eyes close if that feels okay,
or let your gaze rest softly.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Again, breathing in.
And breathing out.
Now notice what is present in your body.
You might notice tension, warmth,
numbness, movement, restlessness, or
stillness.
Whatever is here, simply notice it.
Now bring your attention to your inner
world.
Ask gently: What parts of me are active
right now?
Let the answer come slowly.
<break time="3s"
/>
You may notice a manager part, a worried
part, a tired part, a protective part, a
younger part, a part that wants to do
this correctly, or a part that does not
trust this process.
Each one is welcome to be noticed.
Now ask: How do I feel toward the parts I
am noticing?
If you feel curiosity, compassion, or
calm, notice that.
If you feel judgment, fear, pressure, or
impatience, notice that too. Those
reactions may be parts as well.
Nothing is wrong.
Take a moment to acknowledge any part
that is trying to manage this practice.
You might say inside: I see you. You are
trying to help. You do not have to
disappear. Would you be willing to give
me just a little space?
Now notice whether there is even a small
opening.
A little space. A little breath. A little
softness. A little willingness.
Let that be enough.
Now we will gently invite the qualities
of Self-energy.
Begin with calm.
Ask: Where is calm, even one percent,
available right now?
Maybe in your breath. Maybe in your
hands. Maybe in the space around your
body.
Now curiosity.
Ask: Can I be interested in what is
happening inside without needing to fix
it immediately?
Now compassion.
Ask: Can I sense that these parts are
trying to help me, even when their
strategies are difficult?
Now clarity.
Ask: What do I understand a little more
clearly about my inner world right now?
Now courage.
Ask: What is brave about being present
with myself today?
Now confidence.
Ask: Can I trust that I can listen
slowly, one step at a time?
Now creativity.
Ask: Is there another way to be with this
that my system has not tried yet?
Now connectedness.
Ask: Can I sense connection to my body,
my breath, this moment, or the parts of
me that need care?
Now choose one Self quality that feels
most available.
Let that quality become a gentle
presence.
Not a force. Not a command. Just a warmth
or spaciousness near you.
Now ask: Which part of me most needs this
quality today?
Let one part come forward if it wants to.
Notice it gently.
Where is it? How close is it? What does
it seem to need?
Offer the Self quality to this part.
If calm is present, let calm be near it.
If compassion is present, let compassion
surround it.
If curiosity is present, let curiosity
listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
If courage is present, let courage help
you stay.
You might say: I am here with you. I want
to understand. You do not have to carry
this alone right now.
Notice how the part responds.
<break time="3s"
/>
It does not have to transform. It does
not have to trust you completely.
A small shift is enough.
Now ask this part: What do you want me to
remember after this practice?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now thank the part for whatever it shared
or did not share.
Thank your system for allowing this much
contact.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Bring your attention back to your body.
Feel the support underneath you.
Notice the room around you.
Before you finish, name one Self-energy
quality you want to practice today.
When you are ready, gently return.
Carry these qualities like a lantern
within you. It does not need to shine
brightly all the time. Even a faint light
can help a part know that you are here,
listening, and willing to lead with care.