Welcome to the Self Leadership Mastery
Practice.
This practice is about learning to lead
your inner system with steadiness,
respect, and compassion.
Self leadership does not mean controlling
your parts. It means listening from
enough spaciousness that your parts do
not have to take over completely.
Begin by settling your body.
Let your shoulders soften.
Let your jaw loosen.
Let your breath be natural.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Now bring to mind a recent moment when a
part of you felt activated.
Choose something manageable. Not the
hardest thing. Just a moment when a part
took over, reacted, withdrew, criticized,
protected, or pushed.
Notice the scene gently.
Where were you? What happened? What part
showed up?
Now pause the scene.
Imagine you are watching it from a little
distance.
Ask: Which part of me was leading in that
moment?
Maybe a manager. Maybe a firefighter.
Maybe an inner critic. Maybe a people
pleaser. Maybe an avoidant part. Maybe a
protector that wanted control.
Notice that part without judging it.
Now ask: What was this part trying to
accomplish?
What was it protecting?
What was it afraid would happen?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now ask: How do I feel toward this part
right now?
If you feel frustrated or ashamed, notice
that another part may be present.
Ask that part for a little space too.
Self leadership begins with noticing who
is leading.
Now imagine stepping into the scene with
more Self-energy.
You do not erase the part. You stand near
it.
You might say to the part: I see that you
were trying to help. I understand that
you felt something was at stake. I am
here now. You do not have to handle this
alone.
Now ask the part: What would you need
from me in order to let me lead a little
more next time?
Maybe it needs reassurance, a plan,
protection, a boundary, a slower pace,
more support, or more honesty.
Now imagine the same situation again, but
this time Self is present.
Notice what changes.
Maybe your body feels different. Maybe
your tone changes. Maybe you pause before
responding. Maybe you name what is
happening. Maybe you set a boundary.
Maybe you ask for time. Maybe you do
less, not more.
Let the new possibility be simple.
Now ask your system: What is one
leadership phrase I can use when I notice
a part taking over?
Examples might be: I see you. Let me be
with this. We can slow down. I can listen
without letting you run the whole system.
You do not have to do this alone.
Choose one phrase that feels true.
Now imagine using that phrase during the
next difficult moment.
Let your body feel what it would be like
to pause, breathe, and lead from
Self-energy.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Thank the parts that showed up.
Thank the protectors.
Thank the part of you that is learning to
lead.
When you are ready, return to the room.