Welcome to Safe Place Visualization for
Your Inner Child.
This practice invites you to create an
inner place where a younger part of you
can feel protected, welcomed, and
unhurried.
You do not need to force an image.
You can sense, imagine, or simply choose
the idea of a safe place.
Begin by settling into your body.
Feel the surface underneath you.
Notice the room around you.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Now imagine a place that could feel safe
for a younger part of you.
It may be real or imaginary. It may be
indoors or outdoors. It may be simple or
detailed.
Maybe a cozy room, a treehouse, a garden,
a beach, a cabin, a soft blanket fort, a
quiet library, or a sunny porch.
Let the place form slowly.
Notice the colors. The light. The
temperature. The textures. The sounds.
Notice what makes this place feel safe.
Now imagine adding whatever this younger
part might need.
A soft chair. A blanket. A favorite toy.
A pet. A protective door. A window with
warm light. Art supplies. Music. Space to
move. Space to hide.
Let the place become supportive.
Now ask inside: Is there a younger part
of me that would like to visit this safe
place?
If no part appears, that is okay. The
place can be prepared for later.
If a younger part appears, notice how
close or far away they are.
<break time="3s"
/>
Ask gently: Would you like to come
closer, stay where you are, or just look
at the place from a distance?
Respect the answer.
This place does not demand anything.
Now ask the younger part: What would help
this place feel safer for you?
Maybe they want someone trustworthy
nearby. Maybe they want a locked door.
Maybe they want softness. Maybe they want
brightness. Maybe they want quiet. Maybe
they want play.
Imagine adding what feels welcome.
Now ask: Where would you like to be in
this place?
Let the part choose.
They may sit, stand, hide, explore, play,
or simply watch.
You do not need to direct them.
Now offer a message from Self-energy.
You might say: This place is for you. You
do not have to perform here. You do not
have to explain everything. You can come
here when you need rest. You are allowed
to go slowly.
Notice how the younger part responds.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now imagine a protective boundary around
the safe place.
Only supportive energy is allowed in.
Only what this part consents to can
enter.
The younger part can decide who comes
close.
Now ask: Is there anything you want me to
remember about this place?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now let the younger part know that this
safe place remains available.
They can return here in future practices.
They can adjust it. They can change it.
They can make it more theirs.
Thank the younger part for any contact it
allowed.
Thank your system for creating a place of
care.
Now slowly return attention to your adult
body.
Feel your breath.
Feel your hands.
Feel your feet.
Notice the room.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
When you are ready, return.