Welcome to Body-Based Inner Child
Connection.
This practice helps you notice how a
younger part may communicate through body
sensation.
<break time="3s"
/>
You do not need to create a memory. You
do not need to analyze anything. Just
listen gently to the body.
Begin by finding a comfortable position.
Let your body be supported.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Now scan your body slowly.
Notice your face.
Your jaw.
Your throat.
Your shoulders.
Your chest.
Your stomach.
Your back.
Your hands.
Your legs.
Your feet.
Notice any place that calls your
attention.
It might be tight, heavy, warm, cold,
numb, tingly, restless, or empty.
Just notice.
Now ask: Is there a younger part
connected to this body sensation?
If yes, notice gently.
If no, simply stay with the sensation as
sensation.
Ask the sensation or younger part: What
do you want me to know?
Listen for words, images, emotions, or a
subtle sense.
Now ask: How old does this feeling seem?
Do not force an answer.
Just notice if an age, season, or life
chapter comes to mind.
Now ask: What did this part need back
then?
Maybe comfort, protection, attention,
permission to feel, permission to speak,
or permission to rest.
Now place a hand near the body area if
that feels supportive.
You do not have to touch directly. You
can simply bring warmth or attention
there.
Say gently: I notice you. I am listening.
You do not have to speak perfectly. Your
body is allowed to tell the truth slowly.
Now ask: What would help this area feel
even one percent safer?
Maybe more breath, more space, a
different posture, a blanket, a boundary,
or a word of reassurance.
Offer one small thing.
Now notice whether the sensation changes.
It may soften. It may become stronger. It
may move. It may stay the same.
All responses are allowed.
Now ask the younger part: What do you
want me to carry forward from this
practice?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Thank the body.
Thank the younger part.
Thank any protectors that allowed this
much contact.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Return your attention to the room.
Notice what you can see.
Notice the ground or support beneath you.
When you are ready, gently return.