Welcome to the 6 F’s Protocol Mastery
Practice.
This practice guides you through six
steps for getting to know a part: find,
focus, flesh out, feel toward, befriend,
and fear.
Move slowly.
You do not have to complete every step
perfectly.
Begin by settling into your body.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
The first step is find.
Ask inside: What part of me is asking for
attention right now?
Notice one part.
It might appear as a body sensation,
emotion, thought, image, impulse, or
memory.
The second step is focus.
Bring gentle attention to this part.
Not too close. Not too far. Just enough
to notice it.
Ask: Where do I sense this part in or
around my body?
The third step is flesh out.
Notice more about the part.
Does it have an image? A shape? A color?
An age? A posture? A voice? A feeling?
Let it become more known without forcing.
The fourth step is feel toward.
Ask: How do I feel toward this part?
If you feel curious, compassionate, or
calm, notice that.
If you feel angry, afraid, ashamed,
annoyed, or numb, that may be another
part.
Ask that reacting part if it can give you
a little space.
Now return to the original part.
The fifth step is befriend.
Let the part know you are not here to get
rid of it.
You might say: I want to understand you.
I know you may be trying to help. I am
willing to listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Ask: What do you want me to know?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
The sixth step is fear.
Ask the part: What are you afraid would
happen if you did not do your job?
Listen gently.
This question often reveals what the part
is protecting.
Now thank the part.
You do not have to solve everything.
You have practiced listening.
Ask: What would help you trust me a
little more next time?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Return to the room.
Remember: mastery does not mean rushing
through the steps.
Mastery means returning with patience,
respect, and Self-energy.