Welcome to the Personalized Wound Healing
Action Plan.
This practice helps you choose one small
healing action connected to a wound
pattern you have been noticing.
You do not need to fix the whole wound
today.
You are choosing one compassionate next
step.
Begin by settling your body.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Now gently ask: What wound pattern has
been most present for me recently?
Maybe abandonment, shame, neglect,
betrayal, rejection, helplessness, or
another painful theme.
Choose one pattern to focus on today.
Now ask: How does this wound show up in
my daily life?
Maybe in relationships, work, avoidance,
perfectionism, people pleasing,
withdrawal, self-criticism, urgency, or
numbing.
Notice without judgment.
Now ask: What part of me carries this
wound most strongly?
Let a part come forward if it wants to.
Ask this part: What do you need me to
understand?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now ask: What protector parts try to
prevent this wound from being felt?
Maybe a manager part, a critic, a
planner, a controller, an avoidant part,
a firefighter, or a numbing part.
Thank the protectors for trying to help.
Now choose one small healing action for
this week.
It should be simple.
It might be pausing before
self-criticism, writing one kind sentence
to a younger part, setting one small
boundary, practicing one breath before
reacting, noticing when a protector shows
up, doing one Inner System Map update, or
completing one Life Integration practice.
Now ask: What support do I need to take
this action?
And: What part might resist this action?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now create a gentle plan.
When I notice this wound pattern, I will
pause and offer one small action of care.
Let the action be realistic.
Let it be kind.
Let it be small enough to do.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Thank the parts that showed up.
You are not healing everything at once.
You are building trust one step at a
time.