Welcome to Reparenting Your Inner Child.
This practice helps you offer care to a
younger part from your present-day Self.
Begin by settling into a comfortable
position.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Imagine a younger part of you who may
need attention.
You do not need to force an image.
You may sense an age, a feeling, a
memory, or simply the presence of a
younger part.
Ask gently: Would it be okay if I came
closer?
If the part says no, respect that.
If the part says yes, imagine approaching
with warmth and patience.
Ask: What did you need back then?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Maybe the part needed protection,
comfort, belief, encouragement,
stability, permission to feel, or
permission to be a child.
Now ask: What do you need from me now?
Listen again.
Offer only what feels honest.
You might say: I am here now. You matter
to me. I want to learn how to care for
you. You did not deserve to be alone with
that. We can go slowly.
Now imagine giving this child part
something supportive.
A blanket. A safe room. A hand to hold. A
comforting phrase. A protective boundary.
A place to play.
Let the part choose.
Now ask: How do you feel toward me right
now?
Do not force trust.
If the part is unsure, that is okay.
Trust is built through repeated care.
Ask: What is one way I can show up for
you this week?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Choose one small reparenting action.
Maybe speaking kindly to yourself, taking
rest seriously, setting a boundary,
making space for play, writing to the
younger part, or returning to this
practice.
Now thank the younger part.
Let them know you will keep learning.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Return gently to the room.