Welcome to the Somatic Healing Body Scan.
This practice invites you to listen to
the body as a messenger of parts,
protection, and emotion.
It is not a medical assessment.
It is a gentle awareness practice.
Begin by getting comfortable.
Let your body be supported.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Now bring attention to the top of your
head.
Notice any sensation there.
No need to change it.
Move attention to your forehead.
Your eyes.
Your jaw.
Your mouth.
Notice softness, tension, numbness, or
movement.
Now the throat.
Ask: Is there anything here that wants to
be noticed?
Move to the shoulders.
Notice what they carry.
Move to the chest.
Notice breath, tightness, openness,
heaviness, warmth, or emptiness.
Move to the stomach.
Notice any holding, churning,
contraction, or ease.
Move to the back.
Notice support or strain.
Move to the arms and hands.
Notice whether they want to reach, hold,
push away, protect, or rest.
Move to the hips, legs, and feet.
Notice grounding or restlessness.
Now choose one body area that called your
attention.
Ask: Is there a part connected to this
sensation?
If yes, notice the part gently.
If no, simply stay with the body area.
Ask: What do you want me to know?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Ask: What would help you feel one percent
safer?
Maybe breath, warmth, space, movement, a
hand nearby, a boundary, or a kind
phrase.
Offer that gently.
Now notice if the sensation changes.
It may soften. It may increase. It may
move. It may stay the same.
All of that is okay.
Thank your body for communicating.
Thank any parts that allowed themselves
to be noticed.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Return to the room.
Carry with you the reminder that the body
can be listened to with patience, not
force.