Welcome to the Attachment Pattern
Reflection.
This practice helps you notice how
protective parts may respond to
closeness, distance, repair, and
connection.
<break time="3s"
/>
This is not about labeling yourself.
It is about understanding patterns with
compassion.
Begin by settling your body.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Bring to mind a recent relationship
moment that felt activating.
Choose something manageable.
Not the most overwhelming moment.
Notice what happened.
Did a part want closeness?
Did a part want distance?
Did a part seek reassurance?
Did a part shut down?
Did a part become guarded?
Did a part feel confused, wanting
connection and protection at the same
time?
Now ask: What did my system believe was
at stake in that moment?
Maybe being abandoned, overwhelmed,
rejected, controlled, unseen, too much,
or not enough.
Now notice the protective strategy.
Did you reach, withdraw, please, protest,
freeze, explain, avoid, perform, become
critical, or become silent?
Ask the protective part: What were you
trying to protect me from?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now ask: What did a younger or more
vulnerable part need in that moment?
Maybe reassurance, consistency, space,
repair, honesty, gentleness, or
boundaries.
Ask: What would Self-energy have offered
in that moment?
Maybe calm, clarity, a boundary, a repair
attempt, a pause, a request, or a kind
truth.
Now imagine replaying the moment with a
little more Self-energy present.
Not perfectly.
Just one small change.
What would you say?
What would you do?
What would you not do?
What would you ask for?
Now ask: What attachment pattern do I
want to understand more gently, rather
than judge?
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Thank the parts that protect you in
relationships.
They learned for a reason.
And they can learn new options slowly,
with support.