Welcome to Befriending Your Inner Critic.
This practice is about turning toward the
inner critic with curiosity instead of
fighting it.
The goal is not to let the critic take
over.
The goal is to understand what it is
protecting.
Begin by settling your body.
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Now gently bring to mind the inner
critic.
Notice its voice.
Its tone.
Its favorite messages.
Its posture or image, if it has one.
Do not argue with it yet.
Just notice it.
Ask: Where do I sense this critic in or
around my body?
Now ask: How do I feel toward this
critic?
If you feel angry, ashamed, afraid, or
exhausted, that makes sense.
See if those reactions can give you a
little space so you can listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Now say to the critic: I know you may be
trying to help. I am not here to let you
hurt me. I am here to understand why you
work so hard.
Ask the critic: What are you afraid would
happen if you stopped criticizing me?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Maybe it fears failure, rejection,
humiliation, abandonment, loss of
control, being seen, being too much, or
not being enough.
Now ask: Who or what taught you that
criticism was necessary?
Listen gently.
You do not need a full memory.
Just notice what comes.
Now ask: What are you trying to make me
become?
And: What are you trying to prevent me
from becoming?
Notice the protective intention.
The critic may be harsh because it
believes harshness keeps you safe.
Now say: I understand that you are trying
to protect me. I also need a different
way. Would you be willing to try speaking
to me with more honesty and less attack?
Notice the response.
If the critic is unwilling, ask what it
needs first.
If it is willing, invite it to rephrase
one message.
For example, instead of “You are a
failure,” it might say, “I am scared you
will be rejected.”.
Instead of “You are too much,” it might
say, “I am afraid people will leave.”.
Instead of “You must be perfect,” it
might say, “I need reassurance that
mistakes are survivable.”.
Now thank the critic for revealing what
is underneath.
Ask: What would help you trust
Self-energy more?
Listen.
<break time="3s"
/>
Take a slow breath in.
And let it out.
Let the critic know you will keep
listening, but you will also practice
leading with compassion.
Return gently to the room.